Guide to the Stephen Somerstein Photographs of the 1965 March from Selma to Montgomery 1965 PR 314
New-York Historical Society
Stephen Somerstein photographs of the 1965 march from Selma to Montgomery
New-York Historical Society
Somerstein, Stephen
PR 314
4 Linear feet in 4 boxes
This collection consists of 59 photographs by Stephen Somerstein documenting the 1965 Civil Rights March from Selma to Mongomery, AL. There are some color prints, but most are black and white.
Biographical /Historical Note
Stephen Somerstein was a student at City College of New York and picture editor of the student newspaper when he traveled to Alabama in March 1965 to document the Civil Rights March from Selma to Montgomery.
From March 21 to March 25, 1965, civil rights protesters marched from Selma to the state capitol building in Montgomery, Alabama to demonstrate against the violent resistance that the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and other groups had encountered in their efforts to register African-American voters. On March 25, Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. addressed the crowd of approximately 25,000 supporters from the steps of the Alabama State Capitol. Three months later, President Lyndon Johnson signed the Voting Rights Act of 1965.
After graduating from college, Somerstein did not pursue photography as a career. Instead, he became a physicist and worked at the Harvard-Smithsonian Astrophysical Observatory and at the Lockheed Martin Company. After retiring in 2008, he decided to return to photography. A selection of these photographs were the basis of an exhibition at the New-York Historical Society, Freedom Journey 1965: Photographs of the Selma to Montgomery March by Stephen Somerstein, which was on view from January 16, 2015-October 25, 2015.
Arrangement Note
The photographs are numbered according to numbers assigned by museum staff in preparation for exhibition in 2014, before the collection was accessioned. Prints 47-55 and 65 are not part of the collection.
Scope and Contents Note
This collection consists of 59 photographs which document the 1965 Civil Rights March form Selma to Montgomery, Alabama. Notable individuals featured in the photos include Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., Coretta Scott King, Rosa Parks, James Baldwin, Joan Baez, and Harry Belafonte. A set of exhibition copies of the prints is available for reference.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase, 2015, from the photographer.
African Americans -- Civil rights -- Alabama -- Selma.; African American civil rights workers -- Photographs.; African Americans -- Civil rights.; African Americans -- Suffrage.; Selma (Ala.) -- Race relations.; United States -- Race relations.; Black-and-white photographs.; Photographs.; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968 -- Photographs.; Selma to Montgomery Rights March (1965: Selma, Ala.) -- Photographs.
- [1] CCNY students on bus heading to Alabama., 1965; 1 (Box 1)
- [2] Preparing to leave the City of St. Jude school grounds., 1965; 2 (Box 1)
- [3] Bobby Simmons, civil rights marcher, with "Vote" in white across forehead., 3 (Box 1)
- [4] Civil rights marchers leaving the field of City of St. Jude school., 1965; 4 (Box 1)
- [5] Marchers passing Alabama State Bar building., 1965; 5 (Box 1)
- [6] Two young girls watching civil rights marchers pass by home., 1965; 6 (Box 1)
- [7] Two mothers and babies drinking from milk bottles and young girl watching civil rights marchers., 1965; 7 (Box 1)
- [8] Two men and four children, African-American, watching marchers from their porch., 1965; 8 (Box 1)
- [9] United States Army MPs guarding civil rights marchers on Route 80 at intersection. Road to state capitol in Montgomery, Alabama. (color print), 1965; 9 (Box 1)
- [10] Young boys in the street watching civil rights marchers pass by., 1965; 10 (Box 1)
- [11] Civil rights marchers walking through a town on Route 80, Jefferson Davis Highway, on road to state capitol., 1965; 11 (Box 1)
- [12] Two young marchers with small American flags marching through downtown Montgomery., 1965; 12 (Box 1)
- [13] Front of march preparing to leave City of St. Jude School- John Lewis, Ralph and Juanita Abernathy and others., 1965; 13 (Box 1)
- [14] Front line of marchers at City of St. Jude, from left, (full face), Rev. Arthur Motott, SNCC President John Lewis, Andrew Young, and Sister Mary Leoline., 1965; 14 (Box 1)
- [15] Civil rights marcher conversing with African-American women bystanders, as Selma to Montgomery march moves by., 1965; 15 (Box 1)
- [16] Young civil rights marchers singing as they march on the road to the state capitol in Montgomery, AL., 1965; 16 (Box 2)
- [17] Early arriving civil rights marchers cheering on later arriving marchers- rest stage., 1965; 17 (Box 2)
- [18] Multi-generations of women and children watching civil rights marchers. [color print], 1965; 18 (Box 2)
- [19] African-American woman waving to civil rights marchers. [color print], 1965; 19 (Box 2)
- [20] City dwellers outside their home watching civil rights marchers. [color print], 1965; 20 (Box 2)
- [21] United States Army Military Police guarding civil rights marchers along Route 80, Jefferson Davis Highway., 1965; 21 (Box 2)
- [22] Heckling of the marchers on the streets of Montgomery, Alabama., 1965; 22 (Box 2)
- [23] White bystanders and office workers watching and filming civil rights marchers., 1965; 23 (Box 2)
- [24] Church elders arrayed across steps of Mt. Zion AME Church in Montgomery AL watching civil rights marchers below. [color print], 1965; 24 (Box 2)
- [25] White bystanders watching civil rights marchers on street, downtown Montgomery., 1965; 25 (Box 2)
- [26] Civil rights marchers passing before a mostly African-American crowd on sidewalk outside Askin's Dept. Store, Montgomery., 1965; 26 (Box 2)
- [27] Proud civil rights marchers walking hand-in-hand up to state capitol in Montgomery., 1965; 27 (Box 2)
- [28] Harry Belafonte, Leon Bibb, Joan Baez and Oscar Brand., 1965; 28 (Box 3)
- [29] James Baldwin, Bayard Rustin, A. Philip Randolph, speaker's platform., 1965; 29 (Box 3)
- [30] James Baldwin, Bayard Rustin and A. Philip Randolph, speaker's platform [in front of tree]., 1965; 30 (Box 3)
- [31] Bayard Rustin, Selma March organizer, 1965; 31 (Box 3)
- [32] Dr. Ralph Johnson Bunche on speaker's platform in front of Alabama state house., 1965; 32 (Box 3)
- [33] Coretta Scott King and Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. on speaker's platform befor his speech to 25,000 civil rights marchers., 1965; 33 (Box 3)
- [34] Rosa Parks speaking to 25,000 civil rights marchers. Rev. Ralph Abernathy on left., 1965; 34 (Box 3)
- [35] Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. with civil rights and union leaders singing "We Shall Overcome.", 1965; 35 (Box 3)
- [36] Andrew Young transfixed after singing National Anthem., 1965; 36 (Box 3)
- [37] Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. speaking to civil rights marchers in Montgomery., 1965; 37 (Box 3)
- [38] Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. speaking to civil rights marchers in Montgomery [building in background]., 1965; 38 (Box 4)
- [39] Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. speaking through a sea of microphones at end of march., 1965; 39 (Box 4)
- [40] Ecstatic reaction by spectators to speech by Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., 1965; 40 (Box 4)
- [41] Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. looks out at crowd during his speech to 25,000 civil rights marchers., 1965; 41 (Box 4)
- [42] 25,000 civil rights marchers listening raptly to Dr. King during his speech., 1965; 42 (Box 4)
- [43] Folksinger Joan Baez in front of Alabama state police on top steps of state capitol., 1965; 43 (Box 4)
- [44] State police and government officials watch march from steps of Alabama state capitol., 1965; 44 (Box 4)
- [45] Family watching civil rights marchers, with "Things Go Better With Coke" billboard behind them., 1965; 45 (Box 4)
- [46] Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. seen from rear, speaking to crowd of 25,000., 1965; 46 (Drawer oversize 2NW.9B.27 drawer 14)
- [56] Selma to Montgomery, AL civil rights marchers leaving City of St. Jude school, where they had camped overnight., 1965; 56 (Box 4)
- [57] Civil rights marchers heading up the street to congregate at the foot of the Alabama State Capitol., 1965; 57 (Box 4)
- [58] Jim Leatherer, an Orthodox Jew from Saginaw, Michigan, walked the 53 miles on crutches., 1965; 58 (Box 4)
- [59] Teamsters Union officials gather on field of City of St. Jude school in preparation for the march., 1965; 59 (Box 4)
- [60] Older gentleman at assembly field at City of St. Jude school, ready for the march., 1965; 60 (Box 4)
- [61] Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. and Coretta Scott King at head of 25,000 member civil rights march, leaving the overnight campgrounds of the City of St. Jude school., 1965; 61 (Box 4)
- [62] Young injured boy carried on shoulders of marcher from Canada., 1965; 62 (Box 4)
- [63] Civil rights marchers striding past home with families watching from their porch., 1965; 63 (Box 4)
- [64] Young civil rights marchers carry their American flags past the storefront of Montgomery Seed & Supply Company., 1965; 64 (Box 4)
- [66] From the rooftop of the Brown Printing Company, Army troops monitor civil rights marchers in downtown Montgomery, 1965; 66 (Box 4)
- [67] Black and white pedestrians watching marchers in front of a grocery store on Jefferson Davis Highway., 1965; 67 (Box 4)
- [68] Two opinions; heckler and applauder, reacting to civil rights marchers., 1965; 68 (Box 4)
- [69] Ecstatic, emotional response from Dr. King's staff to his speech in front of the Alabama State Capitol., 1965; 69 (Box 4)